A Guide to the Material By and About Warren Chappell, 1906-1997
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Material By and About Warren Chappell 1906-1997
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10204-bf
ca. 835 items (5 Hollinger boxes and one slipcase, ca. 2 linear feet and one oversize folder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Oak Knoll Books, New Castle, Delaware, on October 26, 2001.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of material by and about Warren Chappell (1904-1991), an artist-in-residence at the University of Virginia, book designer and illustrator, from the collection of Ruth Nuzum, Boulder, Colorado, 1906-1997, ca. 835 items (5 Hollinger boxes and one slipcase, ca. 2 linear feet and one oversize folder). The papers chiefly comprise the correspondence of Warren Chappell with Herb Johnson and Ruth Nuzum, but also include the following correspondents with Chappell and Ruth Nuzum: Janet Anderson, University of Virginia Press; Flora and Franz Hess; William McCleery; Lydia Chappell; Malcolm Cowley; Elizabeth Easton; Anne Freudenberg; Diana Klemin; Dr. Robert L. Leslie; David Vander Meulen; Oak Knoll Books; and Diantha C. Thorpe.
Other material in this collection besides correspondence includes articles by and about Warren Chappell; dust jackets illustrated by Warren Chappell; a slide show and script highlighting five decades of Chappell's work for the 50th Anniversary of the Association of American University Presses; Chappell's autobiography written for the Gale Research Company Something About the Author Autobiography Series; original artwork by Chappell; news clippings about John Updike; news clippings and obituaries about Warren Chappell; photographs of Lydia and Warren Chappell and Chappell relatives; a notebook and "want lists" kept by Ruth Nuzum for material containing any type of work done by Warren Chappell; oversize exhibition posters, artwork, articles, and keepsakes; and page and galley proofs, with the original artwork by Chappell, for Saroyan's Fables by William Saroyan in a separate slipcase.
Contents List
- American Artist Articles featuring or mentioning Warren Chappell 1941-1952 (Box 1)
- American Typecasting Fellowship Newsletter "Recalling Type Design in the Era Before Pictures of Printing" by Warren Chappell 1993 Jul (Box 1)
- Angels & Awakenings Dust Jacket [1980] (Box 1)
- Anna Karenina Dust Jacket [1978] (Box 1)
- Association of American University Presses 50th Anniversary "Five Decades of Warren Chappell's Work" - Slide Show and Script 1987 Jun (Box 1)
- Autobiography of Warren Chappell, Autographed Manuscript [1989] Mar 15 (Box 1)
- Autobiography of Warren Chappell from Something About the Author Autobiography Series, Gale Research Company, with a letter from Warren Chappell, June 7, 1990 [1990] (Box 1)
- Book-of-the-Month-Club ca. 1970-1982 (Box 1)
- Booklet, "How Johnny Reb Outslicked the Yankees, For Johnny at Christmas" hand-drawn by Warren Chappell 1937 (Box 1)
- Chapter & Verse - 3 (electrostatic copy) 1975 Feb (Box 1)
- The Composing Room, Inc. 130 West 46th Street, New York Plan of Gallery 303 n.d.
- Correspondence of Janet Anderson and Ruth Nuzum 1986-1989, 1991 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Flora and Franz Hess 1943-[1964?], n.d. (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Herb Johnson 1963-1972, n.d. (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Herb Johnson re the Supreme Court Series 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Herb Johnson and Related Material regarding the production of John Marshall book 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Herb Johnson and Related Material regarding Published in Paris 1974 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Herb Johnson and Related Material - Notes by Herb Johnson 1980 May 24 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Bill McCleery (Copies) and a postcard from McCleery to Ruth Nuzum 1962-1988 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Ruth Nuzum 1978-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Warren Chappell and Ruth Nuzum, including Lydia Chappell 1989-1991 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Lydia Chappell and Ruth Nuzum 1992-1996 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Chappell Relatives and Ruth Nuzum 1988-1997 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Malcolm Cowley Note to Warren Chappell 1986 Oct 19 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Elizabeth Easton and Ruth Nuzum 1987 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Anne Freudenberg and Ruth Nuzum 1980-1987, 1992, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Neal Jones and Ruth Nuzum 1986 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Diana Klemin and Ruth Nuzum 1980-1983, 1988 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Dr. Robert L. Leslie and Ruth Nuzum 1976, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of David Vander Meulen and Ruth Nuzum 1993-1994 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Miscellaneous Correspondents and Ruth Nuzum 1980-1994 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Oak Knoll Books and Ruth Nuzum 1980, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Diantha C. Thorpe, The Shoestring Press, and Ruth Nuzum and Dust Jacket for Wolf Story 1987-1988 (Box 3)
- Drawing from Don Quixote by Warren Chappell, accompanied by a note to Franz Hess (n.d.) and a much later note from Chappell to Nuzum (1980) concerning its provenance [ca. 1938], 1980 (Box 3)
- Drawings by Warren Chappell 1937, 1989, n.d. (Box 3)
- Engraver's Proof Frontispiece Portrait for the Illustrated Modern Library edition of Shakespeare's Tragedies by Warren Chappell "to George," matted 1944
- "Essences of the Graphic Arts" by Warren Chappell [1949] (Box 3)
- Exhibition Poster for "Littera Scripta Manet Warren Chappell: Fifty Years of Graphic Work" 1983
- Exhibition Poster for "Warren Chappell Artist and Artificer in the Twentieth Century Book World "and Lecture Poster for "Littera Scripta Manet" by David Vander Meulen about Chappell's life work 1994
- The Granite Farm Letters Dust Jacket [1988] (Box 3)
- "Illustrations for Herman Melville's Moby Dick: A Suite of Drawings by Warren Chappell" University of Virginia Art Museum, Thomas H. Bayly Memorial Building 1975 Oct 12-Nov 16 (Box 3)
- Keepsake presented to the Friends of Warren Chappell by The Composing Room, Inc. consisting of a facsimile of a letter from Rudolf Koch, Germany, to Warren Chappell, August 19, 1932, with an English translation on blue paper attached [1932 original]
- Letter of Warren Chappell to Martin K. Speckter 1959 Mar 11 (Box 3)
- Material regarding the Keepsake for the Exhibition about the Art of Willa Cather 1980-1981 (Box 3)
- Material regarding the Production of the Limited Edition Club Moby Dick 1984 (Box 3)
- Material regarding Red Plush by Guy McCrone 1947, 1985 (Box 3)
- Material regarding Production of The Rosa Luxemburg Prophylactic Cooperative A Primer on Communist Civilization 1971 (Box 3)
- "Messing About With Types" by Alex Berlyne, reprinted for the Typophiles 1974
- News clippings regarding Warren Chappell 1970-1983 (Box 3)
- News clippings regarding John Updike 1986 (Box 3)
- Obituaries for Warren Chappell 1991 (Box 3)
- Oral History - Warren Chappell - Interviews 1-9 Transcripts 1978, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Oral History - Selected Pages of Interviews with Harry Scherman and Oscar Ogg from the Book-of-the-Month Club Project 1985 (Box 4)
- Photograph of Lydia and Warren Chappell in Offenbach-A-Main 1931 (Box 4)
- Photographs of Lydia and Warren Chappell and Relatives ca. 1906-1987 (Box 4)
- Postcards sent to Warren Chappell 1908-1910 (Box 4)
- Poster of a letter from Warren Chappell to Ruth Nuzum, mounted on board with illustrations by Chappell [1985]
- Publisher's Weekly Articles featuring or mentioning Warren Chappell ca. 1955-1986 (Box 4)
- Records of Warren Chappell Items Sought by Ruth Nuzum ca. 1938-1986 (Box 4)
- Specimen Broadside of Lydian and Lydian Bold Type and Specimen of Eastern Corporation's Atlantic Bond Paper 1948
- Type Talks "Forum 7 at 8" including Warren Chappell n.d. (Box 4)
- "Want List" for Warren Chappell kept by Ruth Nuzum, with notations by Warren Chappell 1988 Apr 22 (Box 4)
- "Want Lists" for Warren Chappell and Malcolm Cowley kept by Ruth Nuzum n.d., 2 folders (Box 4)
- Alphabetically arranged Notebook of References to Material containing work by Warren Chappell kept by Ruth Nuzum n.d. (Box 5)
- Saroyan's Fables by William Saroyan 1941 (Box 6)
  in a red and black slipcase with four distinct compartments, including page proof sheets for author's correction, galley with author's corrections, galley with printers corrections, and original drawing for illustrations by Warren Chappell of the title page and 27 pictorial capitals.